A Guide to the Papers of John E. Roller 1813-1916
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of John E. Roller 1813-1916
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
9478
This collection consists of ca. 20,000 items(38 Hollinger boxes, ca. 21 linear shelf feet) including 15 ledgers and scrapbooks not shelved in boxes.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The University of Virginia Library purchased these papers from Mr. Harry Dupoy of Mt. Crawford, Virginia, on May 1, 1970.
Biographical/Historical Information
John Edwin Roller (1844-1918), a lawyer, businessman, and politician from Harrisonburg, Virginia, was born in Rockingham County, Virginia, in 1844 of parents of German and French Huguenot descent. At sixteen, he tried to join the Confederate Army but was told that he was too young. He therefore "attached" himself to the 1st Virginia Cavalry and saw action at the first Battle of Bull Run. He attended the Virginia Military Institute from 1862-1863 and was then stationed in Charleston, South Carolina, until late 1864, when he was transferred to the Richmond and Petersburg area.
After the Civil War, he attended Law School at the University of Virginia and was admitted to the Virginia Bar in 1867. He soon became recognized as one of Virginia's leading land lawyers. He served in the Virginia Senate from 1869 to 1873. In 1872, he was appointed Major-General of the Virginia Militia.
Nominally a Democrat, he broke with the party in 1886 over the question of the tariff, and with Republican support, he ran unsuccessfully for Congress that year. In 1888 he ran, again unsuccessfully, as the formal Republican nominee. A man of letters, his library of over two thousand books contained numerous works in German and French.
Scope and Content Information
The collection contains personal, business, and legal correspondence of Roller. There are notes, memoranda, testimony and other court materials, as well as clippings, maps, scrapbooks, maps, ledgers, and genealogy. Two decades of Virginia politics are well represented, especially the 1886 and 1888 Congressional elections. Among the correspondents are John Paul, Berkeley Minor, Alexander R. Pendleton, the American Protective Tariff League, the Anti-Saloon League of Virginia, and the Rockingham County Historical Society.
The first series consisting of correspondence, includes six boxes of outgoing business and legal correspondence in the form of letter press books, 1878-1914, with some letters to Theodore Roosevelt; six boxes of incoming correspondence, 1856-1916, arranged chronologically, dealing with Roller's business and legal affairs; and topical correspondence containing the correspondence of O.B. Roller, letters from the 1886 and 1888 election campaigns, personal correspondence, 1852-1914, and notebooks.
The second series, business materials, contains four boxes of business ledgers, 1813-1916, bills and receipts, cancelled checks, Excellsior Oak Bark papers, and miscellaneous envelopes.
The third series, consisting of legal materials, includes three boxes of case notes and legal memoranda, 1880-1916, court testimony from various cases, subpoenas, Docket of the Virginia Supreme Court of Appeals, 1870's-1890's, lawsuit books, a table of the Maryland family heirs, and the memo book of the Rockingham County Court.
The fourth series, four boxes of miscellaneous papers, consists of news clippings about the Mennonites, miscellaneous maps, a catalog of Roller's library, correspondence of the Rockingham County Historical Society, 1898-1901, newspapers, and scraps of paper.
The last series contains forty-nine scrapbooks and ledgers, concerning agriculture, business, Virginia politics, 1900-1908, literary materials, the Spanish-American War, copious material on Virginia genealogy, the Civil War, and a wide range of miscellanenous materials.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in five series, including 1) Correspondence; 2) Business Materials; 3) Legal Materials; 4) Miscellaneous; and 5) Scrapbooks and Ledgers.
Contents List
- Series I: Correspondence
  - Business and Legal Correspondence - Outgoing 1878 Jul 16-1882 Sep 27, 4 Letter Press Books (Box 1)
  - Business and Legal Correspondence - Outgoing 1882 Sep-1886, 4 Letter Press Books (Box 1-A)
  - Business and Legal Correspondence - Outgoing 1884 Jun 18-1888 Oct, 4 Letter Press Books (Box 2)
  - Business and Legal Correspondence - Outgoing 1892 May-1893 Nov 15, 3 Letter Press Books (Box 3)
  - Business and Legal Correspondence - Outgoing 1893 Nov 15-1895 Dec 5, 4 Letter Press Books (Box 4)
  - Business and Legal Correspondence - Outgoing 1896 Jul-1914 Dec, 3 Letter Press Books (Box 5)
  - Business and Legal Correspondence - Incoming 1856-1889, ca. 180 items (Box 6)
  - Business and Legal Correspondence - Incoming 1890-1895, ca. 200 items (Box 7)
  - Business and Legal Correspondence - Incoming 1896-1900, ca. 250 items (Box 8)
  - Business and Legal Correspondence - Incoming 1901-1909, ca. 230 items (Box 9)
  - Business and Legal Correspondence - Incoming 1910-1911, ca. 300 items (Box 10)
  - Business and Legal Correspondence - Incoming 1912-1916, ca. 150 items (Box 11)
  - Topical Correspondence of Colonel O.B. Roller 1902, ca. 30 items (Box 11)
  - Topical Correspondence with Book Dealers ca. 1911, ca. 20 items (Box 11)
- Series II: Business Materials
  - Business Ledger 1813-1861 (Box 12)
    sale of supplies of Weaver and Carpenter
  - Business Ledger 1846-1861 (Box 12)
    account ledger
  - Business Ledger 1857-1858 (Box 12)
    notebook of supplies ordered
  - Business Ledger 1856-1862 (Box 12)
    lumber orders; also contains lectures on truss construction
  - Business Ledger 1891 (Box 12)
    cash book
  - Business Ledger 1815-1816 (Box 12)
  - Business Ledger 1855-1862 (Box 13)
    accounts
  - Business Ledger 1881-1890 (Box 13)
  - Printed Manuscript ca. 1878-1916, ca. 200 items (Box 13)
    bills and receipts
  - Printed Material ca. 1900 (Box 13)
    insurance policies and contracts
  - Cancelled Checks and Promissory Notes 1870-1916, ca. 2500 items (Box 14)
  - Excellsior Oak Bark Company 1889-1905, ca. 150 items (Box 15)
    Letters, bills, and receipts
  - Miscellaneous Business Envelopes n.d. (Box 15)
- Series III: Legal Papers
  - Manuscript and Typewritten Case Notes and Legal Papers 1880-1916, ca. 75 items (Box 16)
  - Printed and Signed Subpeonas and Judgements 1886-1892, ca. 4 items (Box 17)
  - Argument Docket of the Court of Appeals of Virginia 1877, 1879, 1881, 1891, ca. 4 items (Box 17)
  - Court Testimony in Miscellaneous cases n.d., Typed Manuscript Signed (Box 17)
  - Correspondence and manuscripts regarding the L.L. Shadwell Affair n.d., ca. 75 items (Box 17)
  - Stenographic Notebook n.d., ca. 2 items (Box 17)
  - Typed Letter Signed n.d. (Box 18)
    Note on Legal Cases
  - Ledger - Lawsuit Book 1872-1875 (Box 18)
  - Notebook of Law Lectures 1880 (Box 18)
  - Notebook n.d. (Box 18)
    Table of descent of Maryland Heirs
  - Ledger 1856-1860 (Box 18)
    Memorandum Case Book of Rockingham County Courthouse
- Series IV: Miscellaneous
  - Maps n.d., 3 items (Box 19)
    City Planning Maps
  - "The Incidents of the Retreat to Appomattox" by John Roller n.d., Typed Manuscript (Box 19)
  - News clippings regarding the Mennonites n.d., ca. 200 items (Box 19)
  - Tariff Speech for the GOP by John E. Roller 1908, Typed Manuscript (Box 19)
  - Miscellaneous Maps n.d. (Box 19)
  - Miscellaneous Indices n.d., ca. 7 items (Box 19)
  - Correspondence of the Rockingham County Historical Society 1898 Mar-1901 Mar, Letter Press Book (Box 20)
  - Historical Sketch of the Exhibit ExLibris, by General Roller n.d., notebook (Box 20)
  - Catalogue of the Library of John Roller by room, bookcase, and shelf n.d., notebook (Box 20)
  - Miscellaneous Newspapers dates not provided, ca. 20 items (Box 21)
  - Printed Pamphlet n.d. (Box 22)
    Miscellaneous
  - Miscellaneous Fragments of Letters and Correspondence n.d., 60 items (Box 22)
  - Unidentified Photographs n.d., 75 items (Box 22)
  - Citation to John E. Roller on the Tricentennial of Jamestown's Founding 1907, oversize folder
- Series V: Scrapbooks and Ledgers
  - Scrapbooks, with notes on American and European history, and the American Revolution n.d., 2 scrapbooks (Box 23)
  - Scrapbooks - Oil Industry n.d. (Box 24)
  - Scrapbooks - German-American n.d. (Box 24)
  - Scrapbooks - Curios and Book Notices n.d. (Box 25)
  - Scrapbooks - Political Materials ca. 1900-1908 (Box 25)
  - Scrapbooks of Poetry Clippings n.d., 2 scrapbooks (Box 26)
  - Scrapbooks - Literary Materials n.d. (Box 27)
  - Scrapbooks -Families of Virginia and Maryland (Genealogy) n.d. (Box 27)
  - Scrapbooks -Families of Virginia and Maryland (Genealogy) n.d., 2 scrapbooks (Box 28)
  - Scrapbooks -Families of Virginia and Maryland (Genealogy) n.d., 2 scrapbooks (Box 29)
  - Scrapbooks -Farming and Agriculture n.d., 2 scrapbooks (Box 30)
  - Scrapbooks - Cabell Family ca. 1900-1905 (Box 31)
  - Scrapbooks - Ex-Confederates Visit to Canton, Ohio to see the McKinley Scrapbook ca. 1896-1897 (Box 31)
  - Scrapbooks - Texas Industry and Farming n.d., 3 scrapbooks (Box 31)
  - Scrapbooks - Presidential Campaigns 1908, 4 scrapbooks (Box 31)
  - Scrapbooks - Civil War n.d. (Box 32)
  - Scrapbooks - Farming and Agriculture n.d. (Box 32)
  - Scrapbooks - Civil War n.d., 2 scrapbooks (Box 33)
  - Scrapbooks - Miscellaneous n.d. (Box 34)
  - Scrapbooks - Texas Real Estate, House Plans, Railroads in West Virginia, etc. ca. 1910 (Box 35)
  - Scrapbooks - Miscellaneous n.d. (Box 35)
  - Scrapbooks - Miscellaneous n.d., 2 scrapbooks (Box 36)
  - Scrapbooks - Historical and Literary n.d., 2 scrapbooks (Box 37)
  - Scrapbooks - Miscellaneous n.d., 2 scrapbooks (Box 38)
  - Oak Extract Company Ledger 1905, oversize ledger
  - Business Ledger 1909-1910, oversize ledger
  - Business Ledger 1904-1911, oversize ledger
  - Business Ledger 1911, oversize ledger
  - Business Ledger 1904-1910, oversize ledger
  - Business Ledger 1906-1911, oversize ledger
  - Rockingham School Tax Ledger 1871-1874, oversize ledger
  - Ledger with a list of books, probably the library of General Roller n.d., oversize ledger
  - Scrapbook of Miscellaneous Poetry n.d., oversize scrapbook
  - Scrapbook concerning the Spanish-American War n.d., oversize scrapbook
  - Scrapbook of Miscellaneous Newspaper clippings n.d., oversize scrapbook
  - Scrapbook concerning Texas Agriculture ca. 1910, oversize scrapbook
  - Scrapbook concerning Texas Agriculture ca. 1910, oversize scrapbook
  - Scrapbook of Pictures and Cards n.d., oversize scrapbook
  - Scrapbook of Pictures and Cards n.d., oversize scrapbook